<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd">
<!--
*********************************
Please see LICENSE.txt for this document's license.
*********************************
-->
<sect1 xml:base="nm_gnome.xml" id="sec.nm.gnome">
 <title>Using GNOME NetworkManager</title>
 <indexterm>

  <primary>NetworkManager</primary>

  <secondary>GNOME NetworkManager</secondary>
 </indexterm>

 
 <para>
  In GNOME, NetworkManager can be controlled with the GNOME NetworkManager icon. If the
  network is set up for NetworkManager control, the icon is automatically shown in the
  top bar.
 </para>

 <para>
  If your top bar does not show any network connection icon, GNOME NetworkManager
  is probably not started. Press <keycombo><keycap function="alt"/><keycap>F2</keycap></keycombo> and enter
  <command>nm-applet</command> to start it manually.
 </para>

 <sect2 id="sec.nm.gome.applet.wired">
  <title>Managing Wired Network Connections</title>
  <para>
   If your computer is connected to an existing network with a network
   cable, use the NetworkManager icon to choose the network connection.
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     Click the icon to show a menu with available networks. The
     currently used connection is listed on top of the menu, followed by
     other active connections. </para>
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>Network Settings</guimenu> to get detailed information on 
     all active interfaces.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     To disconnect an active connection, click the 
     <guimenu>OFF</guimenu> button next to <guimenu>Wired</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     If you want to use a different configuration with the wired network,
     open the network configuration dialog and
     add another wired connection as described in
     <xref linkend="pro.nm.configure"/>. Click the NetworkManager icon and
     select the newly configured connection to activate it.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     To switch off all network connections, both wired and wireless,
     right-click the icon and uncheck <guimenu>Enable
     Networking</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 id="sec.nm.gnome.applet.wireless">
  <title>Managing Wireless Network Connections</title>
  <para>
   GNOME NetworkManager lists a number of available visible wireless networks.
   To extend the list, click <guimenu>More
   Networks</guimenu>. The signal strength of each network is also shown in
   the menu. Encrypted wireless networks are marked with a lock icon.
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <title>Connecting to a Wireless Network</title>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     To connect to a wireless network, click the NetworkManager icon and choose
     an entry from the list of available wireless networks.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     If the network is encrypted, a dialog opens. It shows the type of
     encryption the network uses (<guimenu>Wireless Security</guimenu>) and
     holds a number of input fields according to the respective encryption
     and authentication settings. Enter the appropriate credentials.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>To connect to a network that does not broadcast its service set
     identifier (SSID or ESSID), and therefore cannot be detected automatically,
     click the NetworkManager icon and choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Network Settings</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Wireless</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Other</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     In the dialog that opens, enter the connection details and click
     <guimenu>Connect</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     To disable wireless networking, click the icon and click the
     <guimenu>OFF</guimenu> button next to <guimenu>Wireless</guimenu>. This can 
     be useful if you are on a  plane or in any other environment where wireless
     networking is not allowed.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
  <para>
   A wireless network that has been chosen explicitly will remain connected
   as long as possible. If a network cable is plugged in during that time,
   any connections that have been set to <guimenu>Connect
   Automatically</guimenu> will be connected, while the wireless connection
   remains up.
  </para>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 id="sec.nm.gnome.applet.accesspoint">
  <title>Configuring Your Wireless Card as an Access Point</title>
  <para>If your wireless card supports access point mode, you can use NetworkManager for
   configuration.
  </para>
  <note>
   <title>Availability of Options</title>
   <para>
    Depending on your system set-up, you may not be allowed to configure
    connections. In a secured environment, some options might be locked or
    require <systemitem class="username">root</systemitem> permission. Ask your system administrator for
    details.
   </para>
  </note>
  <procedure>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     Click the NetworkManager icon and select <guimenu>Network Settings</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Wireless</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>Click <guimenu>Use as Hotspot</guimenu>, confirm the pop-up and enter 
    the <systemitem class="username">root</systemitem> password to continue.
    
    </para>
    <para>A <guimenu>Network Name</guimenu> (SSID) and a
    <guimenu>Security Key</guimenu> are automatically generated 
    and shown in the <guimenu>Network</guimenu> dialog. 
    The network name will be based on the hostname of your computer. 
    Other devices will need this information to connect to the hotspot that you
    have created.</para>
    <important>
     <title>Unprotected Wireless Networks Are a Security Risk</title>
     <para> To restrict access to your access point and to secure your connection, 
      use encryption. Depending on the abilities of your network card, you can 
      choose between various WEP and WPA–based encryptions. If you are not
      sure which technology is best for you, read
       <xref linkend="sec.wireless.wlan.func.auth"/>. </para>
    </important>
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>To change the SSID, encryption options (WEP, WPA, etc.) or the security 
    key of the hotspot:</para>
    <substeps performance="required">
     <step performance="required">
      <para>Click <guimenu>Options</guimenu> next to the 
    <guimenu>Stop Hotspot</guimenu> button.</para>
     </step>
     <step performance="required">
      <para>Enter the <systemitem class="username">root</systemitem> password to continue.</para>
     </step>
     <step performance="required">
      <para>Change the SSID on the <guimenu>Wireless</guimenu> tab or the 
      encryption details on the <guimenu>Wireless Security</guimenu> tab. </para>
      
      <note>
       <title>WEP 40/128-bit Key (Hex or ASCII)</title>
       <para>When using <literal>WEP 40/128-bit Key</literal> as encryption method, the
         <guimenu>Key</guimenu> length is restricted to either <literal>5</literal>,
         <literal>10</literal>, or <literal>13</literal> characters. Otherwise the
         <guimenu>Save</guimenu> button is inactive.</para>
      </note>
     </step>
     <step performance="required">
      <para>Confirm your changes. After a short delay, the <guimenu>Network</guimenu> 
      dialog will show your changes. </para>
     </step>
    </substeps>
   </step>
  <step performance="required">
   <para>To stop the hotspot and disconnect any users, click 
   <guimenu>Stop Hotspot</guimenu> and confirm your choice in the pop-up 
   dialog.
   </para>
  </step>
 </procedure>
</sect2>
</sect1>
