<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd">
<!--
*********************************
Please see LICENSE.txt for this document's license.
*********************************
-->
<sect2 xml:base="zypper_upgrade.xml" id="sec.update.zypper">
 <title>Distribution Upgrade with zypper</title><indexterm>
 <primary>zypper</primary>
 <secondary>upgrading</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
 <primary>upgrading</primary>
 <secondary>zypper</secondary></indexterm>
 <para>
  With the <command>zypper</command> command line utility you can upgrade to
  the next version of the distribution. Most importantly, you can initiate
  the system upgrade process from within the running system.
 </para>
 <para>
  This feature is attractive for advanced users who want to run remote
  upgrades or upgrades on many similarly configured systems.
 </para>
 <sect3>
  <title>Before Starting the Upgrade with zypper</title>
  <para>
   To avoid unexpected errors during the upgrade process using
   <command>zypper</command>, minimize risky constellations.
  </para>
  <para os="osuse">
   Upgrade from the previous version (e.g., 11.3) to this version
   (11.4)—do not skip any minor version inbetween (this means, do not
   upgrade from 11.2 or earlier to 11.4 in one go). Make sure all available
   11.3 online updates are successfully applied.
  </para>

  <para>
   Close as many applications and unneeded services as possible and log out
   all regular users.
  </para>
  <para os="osuse">
   Disable third party or openSUSE Build Server repositories before starting the upgrade, or
   lower the priority of these repositories to make sure packages from the
   default system repositories will get preference. Enable them again after
   the upgrade and edit their version string to match the version number of
   the distribution of the upgraded now running system.
  </para>
  
  <para os="osuse">
   For more information, see
   <ulink url="http://en.opensuse.org/SDB:System_upgrade"/>.
  </para>
 </sect3>
 <sect3>
  <title>The Upgrade Procedure</title>
  <warning>
   <title>Check Your System Backup</title>
   <para>
    Before actually starting the upgrade procedure, check that your system
    backup is up-to-date and restorable. This is especially important
    because you must enter many of the following steps manually.
   </para>
  </warning>
  <procedure>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     Run the online update to make sure the software management stack is
     up-to-date. For more information, see
     <xref linkend="cha.onlineupdate.you"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     Configure the repositories you want to use as an update source. Getting
     this right is essential. Either use YaST (see
     <xref linkend="sec.y2.sw.instsource"/>) or <command>zypper</command>
     (see <xref linkend="sec.zypper"/>).

     The name of the repositories as used in the following steps could vary
     a little bit depending on your customizations.
    </para>

    
    <para>
     To view your current repositories enter:
    </para>
<screen>zypper lr -u
</screen>
    <tip>
     <title>zypper command names</title>
     <para>
      zypper supports long and short command names. For example, you can
      abbreviate <command>zypper install</command> as <command>zypper
      in</command>. In the following text, the short variant is used.
     </para>
    </tip>
    <substeps performance="required">
     <step os="osuse" performance="required">
      <para>
       Increase the version number of the system repositories from 11.3 to
       11.4; add the new 11.4 repositories with commands such as:
      </para>
<screen>server=http://download.opensuse.org
new_ver=11.4
zypper ar $server/distribution/$new_ver/repo/oss/ openSUSE-$new_ver-Oss
zypper ar $server/update/$new_ver/ openSUSE-$new_ver-Update
</screen>
      <para>
       And remove the old repositories:
      </para>
<screen>
old_ver=11.3
zypper rr openSUSE-$old_ver-Oss
zypper rr openSUSE-$old_ver-Update
</screen>
     </step>
     

     <step performance="required">
      <para>
       Disable third party repositories or other openSUSE Build Server repositories, because
       <command>zypper dup</command> is guaranteed to work with the default
       repositories only (replace <replaceable>repo-alias</replaceable> with
       the name of the repository you want to disable):
      </para>
<screen>zypper mr -d <replaceable>repo-alias</replaceable></screen>
      <para>
       Alternatively, you can lower the priority of these repositories.
      </para>
      <note>
       <title>Handling of Unresolved Dependencies</title>
       <para>
        <command>zypper dup</command> will remove all packages having
        unresolved dependencies, but it keeps packages of disabled
        repositories as long as their dependencies are satisfied.
       </para>
      </note>
      <para>
       <command>zypper dup</command> ensures that all installed packages
       come from one of the available repositories. It does not consider the
       version, architecture, or vendor of the installed packages; thus it
       emulates a fresh installation. Packages that are no longer available
       in the repositories are considered orphaned. Such packages get
       uninstalled if their dependencies can not be satisfied. If they can
       be satisfied, such packages stay installed.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step performance="required">
      <para>
       Once done, check your repository configuration with:
      </para>
<screen>zypper lr -d
</screen>
     </step>
    </substeps>
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     Refresh local metadata and repository contents with <command>zypper
     ref</command>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para os="osuse">
     Pull in zypper and the package management stack from the 11.4
     repository with <command>zypper up zypper</command>.
    </para>
    
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para os="osuse">
     Run the actual distribution upgrade with <command>zypper dup</command>.
     You are asked to confirm the license.
    </para>
    
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     Perform basic system configuration with <command>SuSEconfig</command>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     Reboot the system with <command>shutdown -r now</command>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect3>
</sect2>
