<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd">
<!--
*********************************
Please see LICENSE.txt for this document's license.
*********************************
-->
<chapter xml:base="nm.xml" id="cha.nm">
 <title>Using NetworkManager</title>
 <indexterm>
  <primary>Internet</primary>
  <secondary>connecting to</secondary>
 </indexterm>
 <indexterm>
  <primary>NetworkManager</primary>
 </indexterm>
 <para>
  NetworkManager is the ideal solution for laptops and other portable computers. It
  supports state-of-the-art encryption types and standards for network
  connections, including connections to 802.1X protected networks. 802.1X is
  the <quote>IEEE Standard for Local and Metropolitan Area
  Networks—Port-Based Network Access Control</quote>. With NetworkManager, you
  need not worry about configuring network interfaces and switching between
  wired or wireless networks when you are moving. NetworkManager can automatically
  connect to known wireless networks or manage several network connections
  in parallel—the fastest connection is then used as default.
  Furthermore, you can manually switch between available networks and manage
  your network connection using an icon in the system tray or in the top bar,
  respectively.

 </para>
 <para>
  Instead of only one connection being active, multiple connections may be
  active at once. This enables you to unplug your laptop from an Ethernet
  and remain connected via a wireless connection.
 </para>
 <sect1 id="sec.nm.usecase">
  <title>Use Cases for NetworkManager</title>

  <para>
   NetworkManager provides a sophisticated and intuitive user interface, which enables
   users to easily switch their network environment. However, NetworkManager is not a
   suitable solution in the following cases:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Your computer provides network services for other computers in your
     network, for example, it is a DHCP or DNS server.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Your computer is a Xen server or your system is a virtual system
     inside Xen.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.nm.activate">
  <title>Enabling or Disabling NetworkManager</title>
  <indexterm>

   <primary>NetworkManager</primary>

   <secondary>enabling</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
   On laptop computers, NetworkManager is enabled by default. However, it can be at
   any time enabled or disabled in the YaST Network Settings module.
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     Run YaST and go to <menuchoice> <guimenu>Network Devices</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Network Settings</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     The <guimenu>Network Settings</guimenu> dialog opens. Go to the
     <guimenu>Global Options</guimenu> tab.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     To configure and manage your network connections with NetworkManager:</para>
    <substeps performance="required">
     <step performance="required">
      <para>In the <guimenu>Network Setup Method</guimenu> field, select 
      <guimenu>User Controlled with NetworkManager</guimenu>.</para>
     </step>
     <step performance="required">
      <para>
     Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu> and close YaST.
    </para>
     </step>
     <step performance="required">
      <para>
   Configure your network connections with NetworkManager
   as described in <xref linkend="sec.nm.configure"/>.
  </para>
     </step>
    </substeps>
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>To deactivate NetworkManager and control network the traditional way: </para>
    <substeps performance="required">
     <step performance="required">
      <para>
   In the <guimenu>Network Setup Method</guimenu> field, choose 
   <guimenu>Traditional Method with ifup</guimenu>.</para>
     </step>
     <step performance="required">
      <para>
     Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
    </para>
     </step>
     <step performance="required">
      <para>Set up your network card with YaST using automatic configuration 
      via DHCP or a static IP address. Alternatively, configure your modem with 
      YaST:</para>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
       <listitem>
        <para>For dial-up connections, use
     <menuchoice> <guimenu>Network Devices</guimenu>
          <guimenu>Modem</guimenu>
         </menuchoice>.</para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>To configure an internal or
     USB ISDN modem, select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Network Devices</guimenu>
          <guimenu>ISDN</guimenu>
         </menuchoice>.</para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>To configure an internal or USB
     DSL modem, select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Network Devices</guimenu>
          <guimenu>DSL</guimenu>
         </menuchoice>.</para>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>
     Find a detailed description of the network configuration with YaST in
     <xref linkend="sec.basicnet.yast"/> and
     <xref linkend="cha.wireless.wlan"/>.
    </para>
     </step>
    </substeps>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.nm.configure">
  <title>Configuring Network Connections</title>
  <indexterm>

   <primary>NetworkManager</primary>

   <secondary>configuring</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
   After having enabled NetworkManager in YaST, configure your network connections
   with the NetworkManager front-ends available in KDE and GNOME. The network
   configuration dialogs for both front-ends are very similar. They show
   tabs for all types of network connections, such as wired, wireless,
   mobile broadband, DSL, and VPN connections. On each tab, you can add,
   edit or delete connections of that type. If you hover the mouse pointer over 
   the input fields and options, comprehensive tooltips are displayed. In the KDE 
   configuration dialog, the appropriate tabs are only active if the connection 
   type is available on your system (depending on hardware and software). 
  </para>



  <note os="osuse">
   <title>Bluetooth Connections</title>
   <para>
    Currently, Bluetooth connections cannot be configured with NetworkManager.
   </para>
  </note>

  <para>
   To open the network configuration dialog in GNOME, press 
   <keycombo> <keycap function="alt"/>
    <keycap>F2</keycap>
   </keycombo>
   and enter <command>nm-connection-editor</command>.
   
   
  </para>

  <figure>
   <title>GNOME Network Connections Dialog</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="nm_gnome_tabs.png" width="70%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="nm_gnome_tabs.png" width="50%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
   If you are using KDE, open the main menu and click <guimenu>System
   settings</guimenu>. In the <guimenu>Network and Connectivity</guimenu>
   section select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Network Settings</guimenu>
    <guimenu>Network Connections</guimenu>
   </menuchoice> to open the network
   configuration dialog. 
  </para>

  <figure>
   <title>KDE Network Configuration Dialog</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="nm_kde_tabs.png" width="75%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="nm_kde_tabs.png" width="55%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
   Alternatively, you can also start the configuration dialogs from the NetworkManager
   front-end in the system tray or the top bar, respectively. In KDE, left-click 
   the icon and select <guimenu>Manage Connections</guimenu>. 
   In GNOME, click the icon and select <menuchoice><guimenu>Network Settings</guimenu>
    <guimenu>Options</guimenu>
   </menuchoice>.
  </para>

  <note>
   <title>Availability of Options</title>
   <para>
    Depending on your system setup, you may not be allowed to configure
    connections. In a secured environment, some options might be locked or
    require <systemitem class="username">root</systemitem> permission. Ask your system administrator for
    details.
   </para>
  </note>

  <procedure id="pro.nm.configure">
   <title>Adding or Editing Connections</title>
   <para>
    When configuring network connections with NetworkManager, you can also define
    <literal>system connections</literal> that can be shared by all users.
    In contrast to <literal>user connections</literal>, system connections
    are made available right after NetworkManager is started—before any users
    log in. For more details about both types of connections, refer to
    <xref linkend="sec.nm.sec.types"/>.
   </para>
   
   <note>
    <title>Hidden Networks</title>
    <para>
     To connect to a <quote>hidden</quote> network (a network that does not
     broadcast its service) you have to know the Service Set Identifier
     (SSID) or Extended Service Set Identifier (ESSID) of the network.
     Hidden networks cannot be detected automatically.
    </para>
   </note>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     In the network configuration dialog, click the tab for the connection
     type you want to use.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>Add</guimenu> to create a new connection or select an
     existing connection and click <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     Enter a <guimenu>Connection Name</guimenu> and your connection details.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     You can tie the connection to a certain device, if more than one
     physical device per connection type is available (for example, your
     machine is equipped with two ethernet cards or two wireless cards).
    </para>
    <para>
     If you are using KDE, do so by using the <guimenu>Restrict to
     Interface</guimenu> option. If you are using use GNOME, enter the <guimenu>MAC
     address</guimenu> of the device you want to tie the connection to and
     confirm your settings.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para> For NetworkManager to automatically use a certain connection, activate the
     following option for this connection: <guimenu>Connect
      Automatically</guimenu> (KDE) or <guimenu>Stay connected when
      possible</guimenu> (GNOME).</para>
   </step>
   <step performance="required">
    <para>
     To turn a connection into a <literal>system connection</literal>
     activate <guimenu>System Connection</guimenu> (KDE) or 
     <guimenu>Available to all users</guimenu> (GNOME). To create
     and edit system connections, <systemitem class="username">root</systemitem> permission is required.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>
   After having confirmed your changes, the newly configured network
   connection appears in the list of available networks you get by
   left-clicking the NetworkManager icon. 
  </para>

  <figure>
   <title>KDE NetworkManager—Configured and Available Connections</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="nm_kde_connections.png" width="80%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="nm_kde_connections.png" width="70%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

   <figure>
   <title>GNOME NetworkManager—Configured and Available Connections</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="nm_gnome_connections.png" width="40%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="nm_gnome_connections.png" width="30%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  
 </sect1>
 <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="nm_kde.xml" parse="xml"/>
 <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="nm_gnome.xml" parse="xml"/>
 <sect1 id="sec.nm.vpn">
  <title>NetworkManager and VPN</title>
  <indexterm>

   <primary>NetworkManager</primary>

   <secondary>VPN</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>

   <primary>VPN</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
   NetworkManager supports several Virtual Private Network (VPN) technologies. For
   each technology, <phrase os="osuse">openSUSE</phrase> comes with a base package providing the
   generic support for NetworkManager. In addition to that, you also need to install
   the respective desktop-specific package for your front-end.
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>NovellVPN</term>
    <listitem>

     <para>
      
      To use this VPN technology, install
     </para>
     <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
      <listitem>
       <para>
        <systemitem class="resource">NetworkManager-novellvpn</systemitem> and
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        <systemitem class="resource">NetworkManager-novellvpn-kde4</systemitem> or 
        <systemitem class="resource">NetworkManager-novellvpn-gnome</systemitem>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
     <para>
      NovellVPN support for KDE is not available yet, but is currently being
      worked on.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>OpenVPN</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      To use this VPN technology, install
     </para>
     <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
      <listitem>
       <para>
        <systemitem class="resource">NetworkManager-openvpn</systemitem> and
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        <systemitem class="resource">NetworkManager-openvpn-kde4</systemitem> or
        <systemitem class="resource">NetworkManager-openvpn-gnome</systemitem>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>vpnc (Cisco)</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      To use this VPN technology, install
     </para>
     <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
      <listitem>
       <para>
        <systemitem class="resource">NetworkManager-vpnc</systemitem> and
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        <systemitem class="resource">NetworkManager-vpnc-kde4</systemitem> or
        <systemitem class="resource">NetworkManager-vpnc-gnome</systemitem>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>PPTP (Point-to-Point Tunneling Protocol)</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      To use this VPN technology, install
     </para>
     <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
      <listitem>
       <para>
        <systemitem class="resource">NetworkManager-pptp</systemitem> and
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        <systemitem class="resource">NetworkManager-pptp-kde4</systemitem> or
        <systemitem class="resource">NetworkManager-pptp-gnome</systemitem>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>
   After you have installed the packages, configure your VPN connection as
   described in <xref linkend="sec.nm.configure"/>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.nm.security">
  <title>NetworkManager and Security</title>
  <indexterm>

   <primary>NetworkManager</primary>

   <secondary>security</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
   NetworkManager distinguishes two types of wireless connections, trusted and
   untrusted. A trusted connection is any network that you explicitly
   selected in the past. All others are untrusted. Trusted connections are
   identified by the name and MAC address of the access point. Using the MAC
   address ensures that you cannot use a different access point with the
   name of your trusted connection.
  </para>

  <para>
   NetworkManager periodically scans for available wireless networks. If multiple
   trusted networks are found, the most recently used is automatically
   selected. NetworkManager waits for your selection in case that all networks are
   untrusted.
  </para>

  <para>
   If the encryption setting changes but the name and MAC address remain the
   same, NetworkManager attempts to connect, but first you are asked to confirm the
   new encryption settings and provide any updates, such as a new key.
  </para>

  <para>
   If you switch from using a wireless connection to offline mode,
   NetworkManager blanks the SSID or ESSID. This ensures that the card is
   disconnected.
  </para>

  <sect2 id="sec.nm.sec.types">
   <title>User and System Connections</title>
   <para>
    NetworkManager knows two types of connections: <literal>user</literal> and
    <literal>system</literal> connections. User connections are connections
    that become available to NetworkManager when the first user logs in. Any required
    credentials are asked from the user and when the user logs out, the
    connections are disconnected and removed from NetworkManager. Connections that are
    defined as system connection can be shared by all users and are made
    available right after NetworkManager is started—before any users log in. In
    case of system connections, all credentials must be provided at the time
    the connection is created. Such system connections can be used to
    automatically connect to networks that require authorization. For
    information how to configure user or system connections with NetworkManager, refer
    to <xref linkend="sec.nm.configure"/>.
   </para>
   
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.nm.sec.store">
   <title>Storing Passwords and Credentials</title>
   <para>
    If you do not want to re-enter your credentials each time you want to
    connect to an encrypted network, you can use the desktop-specific tools
    GNOME Keyring Manager or KWalletManager to store your credentials
    encrypted on the disk, secured by a master password.
   </para>
   <para os="osuse;sled">
    In KDE, you can configure if and how to store your credentials. To do
    so, left-click the NetworkManager icon and select <guimenu>Manage
    Connections</guimenu>. Click <menuchoice> <guimenu>Other</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Connection Secrets</guimenu>
    </menuchoice> and select one of
    the following options:
   </para>
   <variablelist os="osuse;sled">
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Do Not Store (Always Prompt)</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       This is useful if you are working in an environment where storing
       credentials is considered a security risk.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>In File (Unencrypted)</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       If you choose this option, your passwords are stored unencrypted in
       the respective connection file that is created for each connection.
 
      </para>
      <warning>
       <title>Security Risk</title>
       <para>
        Storing your network credentials unencrypted is a security risk.
        Everybody who has access to your computer can reuse your
        connectivity and intercept your network connection.
       </para>
      </warning>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>In Secure Storage (Encrypted)</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       If you choose this option, your credentials are stored in
       KWalletManager.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   
   
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.nm.faq">
  <title>Frequently Asked Questions</title>

  <para>
   In the following, find some frequently asked questions about configuring
   special network options with NetworkManager.
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>How to tie a connection to a specific device?</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      By default, connections in NetworkManager are device type-specific: they apply
      to all physical devices with the same type. If more than one physical
      device per connection type is available (for example, your machine is
      equipped with two ethernet cards), you can tie a connection to a
      certain device.
</para>
     <para>
      To do so in GNOME, first look up the MAC address of your device by
      using the output of the command line tool
      <command>ifconfig</command>. Then start the dialog for configuring
      network connections and choose the connection you want to modify. On
      the <guimenu>Wired</guimenu> or <guimenu>Wireless</guimenu> tab, enter
      the <guimenu>MAC Address</guimenu> of the device and confirm your
      changes.
     </para>
     <para>
      If you are using use KDE, start the dialog for configuring network connections
      and choose the connection you want to modify. On the
      <guimenu>Ethernet</guimenu> or <guimenu>Wireless</guimenu> tab, use
      the <guimenu>Restrict to Interface</guimenu> option to select the
      network interface to which to tie the connection.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>
     How to specify a certain access point in case multiple access points with
     the same ESSID are detected?
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      When multiple access points with different wireless bands (a/b/g/n)
      are available, the access point with the strongest signal is
      automatically chosen by default. To override this, use the
      <guimenu>BSSID</guimenu> field when configuring wireless connections.
     </para>
     <para>
      The Basic Service Set Identifier (BSSID) uniquely identifies each
      Basic Service Set. In an infrastructure Basic Service Set, the BSSID
      is the MAC address of the wireless access point. In an independent
      (ad-hoc) Basic Service Set, the BSSID is a locally administered MAC
      address generated from a 46-bit random number.
     </para>
     <para>
      Start the dialog for configuring network connections as described in
      <xref linkend="sec.nm.configure"/>. Choose the wireless connection you
      want to modify and click <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>. On the
      <guimenu>Wireless</guimenu> tab, enter the BSSID.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>How to share network connections to other computers?</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The primary device (the device which is connected to the Internet)
      does not need any special configuration. However, you need to
      configure the device that is connected to the local hub or machine as
      follows:
     </para>
     <orderedlist spacing="normal">
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Start the dialog for configuring network connections as described in
        <xref linkend="sec.nm.configure"/>. Choose the connection you want
        to modify and click <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>. If you are using GNOME,
        switch to the <guimenu>IPv4 Settings</guimenu> tab and from the
        <guimenu>Method</guimenu> drop-down list, choose <guimenu>Shared to
        other computers</guimenu>. If you are using KDE, switch to the
        <guimenu>IPv4 Address</guimenu> or <guimenu>IPv4 Address</guimenu> tab 
        and from the
        <guimenu>Method</guimenu> drop-down list, choose
        <guimenu>Shared</guimenu>. That will enable IP traffic forwarding
        and run a DHCP server on the device. Confirm your changes in NetworkManager.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        As the DCHP server uses port 67, make sure that it is not blocked by
        the firewall: On the machine sharing the connections, start YaST
        and select <menuchoice> <guimenu>Security and Users</guimenu>
         <guimenu>Firewall</guimenu>
        </menuchoice>. Switch to the
        <guimenu>Allowed Services</guimenu> category. If <guimenu>DCHPv4
        Server</guimenu> is not already shown as <guimenu>Allowed
        Service</guimenu>, select <guimenu>DCHPv4 Server</guimenu> from
        <guimenu>Services to Allow</guimenu> and click
        <guimenu>Add</guimenu>. Confirm your changes in YaST.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </orderedlist>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>
     How to provide static DNS information with automatic (DHCP, PPP, VPN)
     addresses?
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      In case a DHCP server provides invalid DNS information (and/or
      routes), you can override it. Start the dialog for configuring network
      connections as described in <xref linkend="sec.nm.configure"/>. Choose
      the connection you want to modify and click <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>.
      If you are using GNOME, switch to the <guimenu>IPv4 Settings</guimenu>
      tab, and from the <guimenu>Method</guimenu> drop-down list, choose
      <guimenu>Automatic (DHCP) addresses only</guimenu>. If you are using
      KDE, switch to the <guimenu>IPv4 Address</guimenu> or 
      <guimenu>IPv4 Address</guimenu> tab, and from the
      <guimenu>Method</guimenu> drop-down list, choose <guimenu>Automatic
      (DHCP) addresses only</guimenu>. Enter the DNS information in the
      <guimenu>DNS Servers</guimenu> and <guimenu>Search Domains</guimenu>
      fields. From the drop-down list at the top of the tab, select
      <guimenu>Routes</guimenu> if you want to <guimenu>Ignore automatically
      obtained routes</guimenu>. Confirm your changes.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>
     How to make NetworkManager connect to password protected networks before a user
     logs in?
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Define a <literal>system connection</literal> that can be used for
      such purposes. For more information, refer to
      <xref linkend="sec.nm.security"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.nm.trouble">
  <title>Troubleshooting</title>
  <indexterm>

   <primary>NetworkManager</primary>

   <secondary>troubleshooting</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
   Connection problems can occur. Some common problems related to NetworkManager
   include the front-end not starting or a missing VPN option. Methods for
   resolving and preventing these problems depend on the tool used.
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>NetworkManager Front-End Does Not Start</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The GNOME and KDE NetworkManager front-ends start automatically if the network is
      set up for NetworkManager control. If the front-end does not start, check if NetworkManager
      is enabled in YaST as described in
      <xref linkend="sec.nm.activate"/>. Then make sure that the appropriate
      package for your desktop environment is also installed. If you are
      using KDE 4, the package is
      <systemitem class="resource">plasmoid-networkmanagement</systemitem>.
      For GNOME users the package is
      <systemitem class="resource">NetworkManager-gnome</systemitem>.
     </para>
     <para>
      If the desktop front-end is installed but is not running for some reason,
      start it manually with <keycombo><keycap function="alt"/><keycap>F2</keycap></keycombo> and <command>nm-applet</command> (GNOME) or
      by clicking the <guimenu>Panel
      Tool Box</guimenu> and choosing <guimenu>Add Widgets</guimenu>. (KDE)
      Double-click the <guimenu>Network Management</guimenu> entry and
      click the <guimenu>Panel Tool Box</guimenu> again.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>NetworkManager Front-End Does Not Include the VPN Option</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Support for NetworkManager, front-ends, and VPN for NetworkManager is distributed in separate
      packages. If your NetworkManager front-end does not include the VPN option, check
      if the packages with NetworkManager support for your VPN technology are
      installed. For more information, see <xref linkend="sec.nm.vpn"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>No Network Connection Available</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      If you have configured your network connection correctly and all other
      components for the network connection (router, etc.) are also up and
      running, it sometimes helps to restart the network interfaces on your
      computer. To do so, log in to a command line as <systemitem class="username">root</systemitem> and run
      <command>rcnetwork restart</command>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.nm.more">
  <title>For More Information</title>

  <para>
   More information about NetworkManager can be found on the following Web sites and
   directories:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>NetworkManager Project Page</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <ulink url="http://projects.gnome.org/NetworkManager/"/>
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>KDE NetworkManager Front-End</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <ulink url="http://userbase.kde.org/NetworkManagement"/>
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Package Documentation</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Also check out the information in the following directories for the
      latest information about NetworkManager and the GNOME and KDE NetworkManager front-ends:
     </para>
     <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
      <listitem>
       <para>
        <filename>/usr/share/doc/packages/NetworkManager/</filename>,
       </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
       <para>
        <filename>/usr/share/doc/packages/NetworkManager-gnome/</filename>.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
